CHAPTER 11 THE NEST OF THE missile THRUSH For two or 3 minutes he stood
looking round him, while Mary watched him, and then he began to walk about softly,
even more lightly than Mary had walked the first time she had found herself inside the four
walls. His eyes seemed to be taking in everything— —the gray trees with the gray
creepers climbing over them and hanging from their branches,
the tangle on the walls and among the grass, the evergreen alcoves with the
stone seats and tall flower NS standing in them. "I never thought I'd see this
place," he said at last, in a whisper. "Did you know about it?" asked
Mary. She had spoken aloud and he made a
sign to her. "We must talk low," he said, "or someone will hear us and wonder what's
to do in here." "Oh! I forgot!" said Mary, feeling frightened and putting her hand quickly
against her mouth. "Did you know about the garden?" she asked again when she had
recovered herself. Dickon nodded. "Martha told me there was one as no one ever
went inside," he answered. "Us used to wonder what it was like." He stopped and
looked round at the lovely gray tangle about him, and his round eyes looked queerly
happy he the next nests as'll be here come springtime," he said. "It'd be the
safest nesting place in England. No one never coming near and tangles of trees
and roses to build in. I wonder all the birds on the Moore don't build
here." Mistress Mary put her hand on his arm again without knowing it. "Will there
be roses?" she whispered. "Can you tell? I thought perhaps they were all
dead." "Eh! No! Not them— —not all all of them he answered. "Look here!" He stepped over to
the nearest tree— —an old, old one with gray lyen all over its bark, but
upholding a curtain of tangled sprays and branches. He took a thick knife out of
his pocket and opened one of its blades. "There's lots of dead wood as
ought to be cut out," he said and there's
a lot of old wood, but it made some new
last year. This here is a new bit," and he touched a chute which looked brownish
green instead of hard, dry gray. Mary touched it herself in an eager, reverent
way. "That one?" she said. "Is that one quite alive— —quite?" Dickon curved his wide
smiling mouth. "It's as wick as you or me," he said; and Mary remembered that Martha
had told her that "wick" meant "alive" or "lively." "I'm glad it's wick!" she cried
cried out in her whisper. "I want them all to be wick. Let us go around the garden
and count how many wick ones there are." She quite panted with eagerness, and
Dickon was as eager as she was. They went from tree to tree and from bush to bush.
Dickon carried his knife in his hand and showed her things which she thought
wonderful. "They've run wild," he said, "but the strongest ones has fair thrived on
it. The delicat ones has died out, but the others has growed and growed and spread
and spread, till there's a wonder. See here!" and he pulled down a thick gray dry looking
branch. "A body might think this was dead wood, but I don't believe it is— —down to
the rote I'll cut it low down and see." He knelt and with his knife cut the
lifeless looking branch through, not far above the earth. "There!" he said exultantly.
"I told thee so. There's green in that wood yet. Look at
it." Mary was down on her knees before he spoke, gazing with all her might. "When it
looks a bit greenish and juicy like that, it's wick," he explained. "When the inside
is dry and breaks easy, like this here piece I've cut off, it's done for. There's
a big root here is all this live wood sprung out of and if the old Woods cut
off and it's dug round and took care of they'll be—" he stopped and lifted his
face to look up at the climbing and hanging sprays above him—" —"there'll be a
fountain of roses here this summer." They went from bush to bush and
from tree to tree. He was very strong and clever with his knife and knew how to
cut the dry and dead wood away, and could tell when an unpromising bow or twig had
still green life in it.
In the course of half an hour Mary thought she could tell too, and when he
cut through a lifeless looking branch she would cry out joyfully under her
breath when she caught sight of the least shade of moist
green. The spade, and hoe, and fork were very useful. He showed her how to use the fork
while he dug about roots with the spade and stirred the earth and let the air in.
They were working industriously around one of the biggest standard roses when
he caught sight of something which made him utter an exclamation of
surprise. "Why!" he cried, pointing to the grass a few feet away. "Who did that there?"
It was one of Mary's own little clearings round the pale green points. "I did it," said
Mary. "Why, I thought there didn't know nothing about gardening he exclaimed. "I
don't," she answered, "but they were so little, and the grass
was so thick and strong, and they looked as if they had no room to breathe. So I
made a place for them. I don't even know what they
are dick and went and knelt down by them, smiling his wide
smile th was right," he said. "A gardener couldn't have told thee better. They'll
grow now like Jack's Beanstalk They're crocuses and snow drops and these here
is n s SES turning to another patch and here's Daffy Down dillies Eh! they will
be a sight." He ran from one clearing to another th has done a lot of work for
such a little wench," he said, looking her over. "I'm growing fatter," said Mary, "and
I'm growing stronger. I used always to be tired. When I dig I'm not tired at all. I
like to smell the earth when it's turned up." "It's rare good for thee,"
he said, nodding his head wisely. "There's not as nice as the smell a good clean
earth, except the smell of fresh growing things when the rain falls on them I get
out on the mo many a day when it's raining and I lie under a bush and
listen to the soft Swisher drops on the heather and I just sniff and sniff. My
nose end fair quivers like a rabbit's, mother says." "Do you never catch cold?" inquired
Mary, gazing at him wonderingly. She had never seen such a funny boy, or such a
nice one. "Not me," he said, grinning. "I never catched cold since I was born. I wasn't
brought up NES enough. I've chased about the mo in all weathers same as the
rabbits does. Mother says I've sniffed up too much fresh air for 12 years to ever
get to sniffing with cold. I'm as tough as a whitethorn
knobstick." He was working all the time he was talking and Mary was following him
and helping him with her fork or the trowel. "There's a lot of work to do here!"
he said once, looking about quite exultantly. "Will you come again and help
me to do it?" Mary begged. "I'm sure I can
help, too. I can dig and pull up weeds, and do whatever you tell me. Oh! do come,
Dickon!" "I'll come every day if thou wants me, rain or shine," he answered stoutly.
"It's the best fun I ever had in my life— —shut in here and wakening up a
garden." "If you will come," said Mary, "if you will help me to make it alive
I'll— —I don't know what I'll do," she ended helplessly. What could you do for a boy
like that? "I'll tell thee what thou do," said Dickon, with his happy grin thou get
fat and I'll get as hungry as a young fox and they'll learn how to talk to the
robin same as I do. Eh! we'll have a lot of
fun." He began to walk about, looking up in the trees and at the walls and bushes
with a thoughtful expression. "I wouldn't want to make it look like a gardener's garden, all
clipped and and span, would you?" he said. "It's nicer like this with things
running wild and swinging and catching hold of each other." "Don't let us make it tidy," said
Mary anxiously.
"It wouldn't seem like a secret garden if it was tidy Dickens stood rubbing his Rusty red
head with a rather puzzled look. "It's a secret garden sure enough," he
said, "but seems like someone besides the robin must have been in it since it was
shut up 10 years ago." "But the door was locked and the key
was buried," said Mary. "No one could get in."
"That's true," he answered. "It's a queer place. Seems to me as if there had been a
bit of pruning done here and there, later than 10 years
ago." "But how could it have been done?" said Mary. He was examining a branch of a
standard rose and he shook his head I how could it!" he murmured. "With the door
locked and the key buried." Mistress Mary always felt that
however many years she lived she should never forget that first morning when her
garden began to grow.
Of course, it did seem to begin to grow for her that morning. When Dickon began
to clear places to plant seeds, she remembered what Basil had sung at her
when he wanted to tease her. "Are there any flowers that look like bells?" she
inquired LLY of the valley does," he answered, digging away with the TRL and
there's Canterbury bells and campanulas." "Let us plant some," said Mary.
"There's lies of the valley here already; I saw them They'll have grow too close
and we'll have to separate them but there's plenty the other ones takes two years to
bloom from seed, but I can bring you some bits of plants from our cottage garden.
Why does that want him Then Mary told him about Basil and
his brothers and sisters in India and of how she had hated them and of their
calling her "Mistress Mary Quite Contrary."
"They used to dance around and sing at me.
They sang Mistress Mary, quite contrary, How does your garden grow? With silver bells,
and cockal shells, And marry Golds all in a row.' I just remembered it and it made
me wonder if there were really flowers like silver bells." She frowned a little and gave her
TR a rather spiteful dig into the earth. "I wasn't as contrary as they
were." But Dickon laughed e he said, and as he crumbled the rich black soil she saw
he was sniffing up the scent of it, "there
doesn't seem to be no need for no one to be contrary when there's flowers and
such like and such lots of friendly wild things running about making homes for
themselves, or building nests and singing and whistling does there?"
Mary, kneeling by him holding the seeds, looked at him and stopped
frowning. "Dickon," she said. "You are as nice as Martha said you were. I like you, and
you make the fifth person. I never thought I should like five people
Dickens sat up on his heels as Martha did when she was polishing the
great He did look funny and delightful, Mary thought, with his round blue eyes
and red cheeks and happy looking Turned Up nose. "Only five folk as thou likes?" he
said. "Who is the other four?" "Your mother and Martha," Mary checked
them off on her fingers, "and the robin and Ben weather staff Dickon laughed so
that he was obliged to stifle the sound by putting his arm over his mouth. "I know
that thinks I'm a queer lad," he said, "but I think Thou art the queerest little
lass I ever saw." Then Mary did a strange thing. She leaned forward and asked him a
question she had never dreamed of asking anyone before. And she tried to ask it in
Yorkshire because that was his language and in India a native was always pleased if you knew his
speech. "Does that like me?" she said. "Eh!" he answered heartily, "that I does. I likes
the wonderful and so does the robin, I do believe!" "That's two, then," said Mary.
"That's too for me." And then they began to work harder than ever and more
joyfully. Mary was startled and sorry when she heard the big clock in the
courtyard strike the hour of her midday dinner. "I shall have to go," she said
mournfully. "And you will have to go too, won't you?" Dickon grinned. "My dinner's
easy to carry about with me," he said.
"Mother always lets me put a bit of something in my pocket." He picked up his
coat from the grass and brought out of a pocket a lumpy little bundle tied up in
a quiet clean, coarse, blue and white handkerchief. It held two thick pieces of
bread with a slice of something laid between them. "It's oftenest not but bread,"
he said, "but I've got a fine slice of fat bacon with it today Mary thought it
looked a queer dinner, but he seemed ready to enjoy it.
"Run on and get thy vitual he said. "I'll be done with mine first. I'll get some
more work done before I start back home." He sat down with his back against a
tree. "I'll call the robin up," he said, "and give him the rind of the bacon to peck
at. They likes a bit of fat wonderful." Mary could scarcely bear to
leave him. Suddenly it seemed as if he might be a sort of wood fairy who might
be gone when she came into the garden again. He seemed too good to be true. She
went slowly halfway to the door in the wall and then she stopped and went
back. "Whatever happens, you— —you never would tell?" she said. His poppy colored cheeks were
distended with his first big bite of bread and bacon, but he managed to smile
encouragingly. "If there was a missile thrush and showed me where thy nest was,
does that think I'd tell anyone Not me," he said thou art as safe as a missile
thrush." And she was quite sure she